Edward A. Harris Papers
Edward A. Harris Papers
1928-1961
Harris, Edward A., 1910-1976.
3.0 linear ft., 16 scrapbooks.
Papers of the American newspaper journalist.
Correspondence (1929-1958); news story research material; book and short story manuscripts; photographs; published material by and about Harris; and sixteen scrapbooks of clippings by Harris and others.
149036
Biographical History
Edward A. Harris (1910-1976) was an American newspaper journalist. Born in St. Louis, he graduated from Washington University in St. Louis in 1933 and joined the staff of the St. Louis Star-Times as a columnist and general reporter. In 1940 he took a position as City Hall reporter for the St. Louis Post-Dispatch, later becoming a regular reporter and local political writer. He was assigned to the Post-Dispatch's Washington Bureau in 1943 and for the next ten years covered numerous White House news conferences and events, Senate and House hearings, presidential campaigns and national conventions. During his Washington tenure, he concentrated on civil liberties issues and corruption investigations, winning a Pulitzer Prize in 1916. From 1951-1957 he served as West Coast bureau Chief for the Post-Dispatch, taking a leave of absence in 1957 to obtain a Master's Degree from U.C.L.A. In 1959, Harris bought Hidden Valley Farm, a 912-acre property in the foothills of the Blue Ridge Mountains in Virginia where he farmed, wrote books, and contributed a weekly syndicated agricultural column entitled "Down on the Farm."
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Edward A. Harris Papers consists of correspondence, subject files, manuscripts, and published material.
Correspondence consists of incoming letters, dating from 1929 to 1958. Subject files is comprised of materials from Edward Harris's high school, college, and post-graduate years (1928-58). Also included are office memos (1941-1947) between the St. Louis office and Harris. Early news stories contains news story material for the St. Louis Star Times and the St. Louis Post-Dispatch (1933-1952). There are file folders (1943-1954) on eight major news stories which Harris wrote for the St. Louis Post-Dispatch, as well as file folders on the Presidential convention and campaigns (1919-1952). Stevenson campaign clips (1952), syndicated column "Down on the Farm," promotional material, and some miscellaneous material are also included. Manuscripts are of books, short stories, and a teleplay. The manuscripts are all typescript, except for one book holograph. Published material consists of a book (1958), articles about Harris (1934-1953, articles by Harris, (1934-1952) and one short story by Harris (1933), as well as an article by others (1916). There is a file folder of newspaper clippings (1941-1954) by Harris and a file folder of newspaper clippings (1948-1953) by others. Scrapbooks of clippings cover nearly twenty years (1943-1961).
Arrangement of the Collection
Correspondence is arranged alphabetically and then chronologically. Subject files are arranged alphabetically by topic. Manuscripts and published material are arranged alphabetically by type and within that by title. Scrapbooks are arranged chronologically.
Subject and Genre Headings
Journalism; Harris, Edward A., 1910-1976.; Journalism.; Journalists -- United States.; Articles.; Clippings (information artifacts); Correspondence.; Manuscripts for publication.; Photographs.; Scrapbooks.; Journalists.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Edward and Miriam Harris.
Inventory
- Correspondence
  - Ambrose, Joe, 1946 (Box 1)
  - "Art", 1946 (Box 1)
  - Balch, Jack, 1945-1958 (Box 1)
  - Blake, Thomas D., 1946 (Box 1)
  - Boone, Marion, 1946 (Box 1)
  - Brant, Irving, 1944 (Box 1)
  - Buckhart, Jim, 1957 (Box 1)
  - Coghlan, Ralph, 1946 (Box 1)
  - Congelman, Jim, 1946 (Box 1)
  - Davidson, C. Girard, 1948 (Box 1)
  - Elmore, Frank H., Jr, 1946 (Box 1)
  - Fitzpatrick, D. R., 1946-1948 (Box 1)
  - Fleischer, Nat S., 1936 (Box 1)
  - Flores, Alfonso M., 1946 (Box 1)
  - "Gil", 1946 (Box 1)
  - Goldstein, Al, 1946 (Box 1)
  - Goldstein, J. Walter, 1946 (Box 1)
  - Gottlieb, Ferd, 1946 (Box 1)
  - Grant, Donald, 1946 (Box 1)
  - Harris, Robert E. G., 1958 (Box 1)
  - Henry, J. Porter, Jr., 1946 (Box 1)
  - Kaplan, Jack, 1958 (Box 1)
  - Kenamore, Charles, 1946 (Box 1)
  - Kirschten, Ernest, 1946 (Box 1)
  - Laddin, Nat, 1946 (Box 1)
  - Loeb, Mrs, Virgil, 1946 (Box 1)
  - McAfee9 Wes, 1946 (Box 1)
  - Margo, 1946 (Box 1)
  - Martin, John, 1946 (Box 1)
  - Mockler, Stan, 1946 (Box 1)
  - Parry, Thomas D., 1946 (Box 1)
  - Reese, B. H. (B. H. R.), 1948 (Box 1)
  - Ruddy, Edward A., 1946 (Box 1)
  - Schless, Frank H., 1946 (Box 1)
  - Schoknecht, A. C. C., 1946 (Box 1)
  - Shepley, Ethan A., 1958 (Box 1)
  - Skinner, Lemoine, Jr., 1946 (Box 1)
  - Tavenner, Eugene, 1929 (Box 1)
  - Terral, Rufus, 1946 (Box 1)
  - Thompson, Ted, 1946 (Box 1)
  - Throop, George R., 1932 (Box 1)
  - Toberman, Walter H., 1946 (Box 1)
  - Turner, Fitzhugh, 1958 (Box 1)
  - Wheeler, Crawford, 1946 (Box 1)
  - Willier, Robert A., 1946 (Box 1)
- Subject files
  - Blue Ridge School of Journalism (Box 2)
  - Education
    - High School, U. City, 1928-1929 (Box 2)
    - College, Washington University, 1929-1933 (Box 2)
    - Taster's Degree, U.C.L.A., 1957-1958 (Box 2)
  - Memos
    - Office Private, 1945-1953 (Box 2)
    - Office Pulitzer Prize, 1941-1947 (Box 2)
  - News Stories, early ( St. Louis Star & Times and St. Louis Post-Dispatch), 1933-1947 (Box 2)
  - News Stories, St. Louis Post-Dispatch
    - American President Lines, 1952 (Box 2)
    - California Assignment, 1954-1957 (Box 2)
    - California Assignment, 1956 (Box 2)
    - California Oil Case, 1953-1954 (Box 3)
    - California Oil Inquiry, 1945 (Box 3)
    - China Lobby, 1948-1951 (Box 3)
    - Colonial Airlines, 1951 (Box 3)
    - Ellen Knauff Case, 1949-1951 (Box 3)
    - Mexican Oil, 1946-1949 (Box 3)
    - Col. John P. Monroe Case, 1943 (Box 4)
    - Tidelands Oil, Edwin W. Pauley, 1945 (Box 4)
  - Presidential Convention and Campaign, 1949-1952 (Box 4)
  - Radio Station KSD St. Louis, 1944 (Box 4)
  - Senate Banking and Currency Committee Memorandum, 1949 (Box 4)
  - Stevenson Campaign Clips, 1952 (Box 4)
  - Syndicated Column "Down on the Farm" Promotional Material, 1960-1961 (Box 4)
- Manuscripts
  - Books
    - And Swift the Earth, about 1935; typescript, bound, 278 pp. (Box 4)
    - Ever Since Eve Bit the Apple or Sex and the Married Woman, typescript, unbound, 230 pp. (Box 4)
    - Love Thy Neighbor, holograph, bound and unbound, 277 pp. (Box 5)
  - Short stories, magazine
    - "The Coffee Was Cold", typescript (Box 5)
    - "Now here's the Rub", typescript carbon (Box 5)
    - "Piggy Bank Tarn", typescript carbon 22pp (Box 5)
    - "A Walk Around the Block", typescript 31pp (Box 5)
  - Teleplay
    - A Walk Around the Block, typescript 121pp (Box 5)
- Published materials
  - Books
    - Love Thy Neighbor, Exposition Press, New York. Autographed., 1951 (Box 5)
  - Articles about Harris
    - Editor and Publisher, Oct. 20, 1931 (Box 5)
    - Life, Dec. 23, 1912 (Box 5)
    - Collier's, Dec. 16, 1950 (Box 5)
    - Saturday Evening Post, March 10, 1951 (Box 5)
    - Newsweek, Dec. 14, 1953 (Box 5)
  - Articles by Harris
    - The High School Teacher, Dec. 1934 (Box 5)
    - Negro Digest, April 1944 (Box 6)
    - The New Republic, Aug. 28, 1944; 2 items (Box 6)
    - Liberty, Oct. 21, 1914 (Box 6)
    - Liberty, Dec. 2, 1911 (with Marquis J. Childs) (Box 6)
    - The Nation, May 5, 1945 (Box 6)
    - Washington News Digest, Feb. 1946 (Box 6)
    - Digest and Review, March 1946 (Box 6)
    - New Republic, Jan. 20, 1947 (Box 6)
    - Magazine Digest, Jan. 1948 (Box 6)
    - New Republic, Aug. 1, 1949 (Box 6)
    - New Republic, March 2, 1952 (Box 6)
  - Articles by Others
    - New Republic, Aug. 5, 1946 (Box 6)
  - Short Story
    - The All-America Sport Magazine, Sept. 1938 (Box 6)
  - Newspaper clippings by Harris
    - 1941-1954 (Box 6)
  - Newspaper clippings by others
    - 1948-1953 (Box 6)
- Scrapbooks
  - Correspondence, 1943-1944; Correspondence, incoming, letters of commendation and congratulations (very few clippings) on Harris' news stories from OWI Director Elmer Davis, Ben "B. R." Reese, Ralph Coghlan, and Dan Fitzpatrick of the St. Louis Dispatch, Senator Harry S. Truman, James C. Hagerty, Charles G. Ross and many others (Volume 1)
  - Clippings of Harris' news stories, 1943-1944; from Washington, D. C. for St Louis Dispatch (Volume 2)
  - Clippings of Harris' news stories, 1944; from Washington, D. C. for St. Louis Dispatch (Volume 3)
  - Clippings of Harris' news stories, 1944; from Washington, D. C. for St. Louis Dispatch (Volume 4)
  - Clippings of Harris' news stories on Tidelands Oil, 1945; from Washington, D. C. for St. Louis Dispatch; Fitzpatrick's cartoons are also Included (Volume 5)
  - Clippings of Tidelands Oil Scandal by Ed Harris and others, 1946; Harris' news stories were filed from Washington, D. C. for St. Louis Dispatch. Includes correspondence from Senator Charles Tobey, Harold L. Ickes, Jonathan Daniels, Herbert Bayard Swope, Joseph Pulitzer, Ralph Goghlan, Ben Reese, and Daniel Fitzpatrick from the St. Louis Dispatch. (Volume 6)
  - Clippings of China Lobby Series by Ed Harris and others, 1949-1950; several incoming letters; Harris' news stories were filed from Washington, D. C. for the St. Louis Dispatch. also cartoons by Herblock and Fitzpatrick. (Volume 7)
  - Clippings of news stories by Ed Harris and others, 1949-1952; Harris' news stories were filed from Washington, D. C. for the St. Louis Dispatch; includes considerable correspondence, much of it from President Truman, White House Press Secretaries, Gov. Adlai Stevenson, and St. Louis Dispatch memos (Volume 8)
  - Clippings of Ellen Knauff Case by Ed Harris and others, 1950; includes cartoons by Fitzpatrick; Harris' news stories were filed from Washington, D. C. for the St. Louis Dispatch (Volume 9)
  - Clippings of news stories by Ed Harris and others, 1953; Harris' news stories were filed from Washington, D. C. for the St. Louis Dispatch; also some correspondence, including a letter from Supreme Court Justice Felix Frankfurter, and St. Louis Dispatch Office Memos (Volume 10)
  - Clippings of news stories by Ed Harris and others, 1954; Harris' news stories were filed from Washington, D. C. for the St. Louis Dispatch (Volume 11)
  - Clippings of news stories by Ed Harris, 1955; from the West Coast for the St. Louis Dispatch; includes correspondence from the Rev. Donald Curtis, Claire Rochelle, Paul Butler, Chairman of the National Democratic Committee, Robert M. Hutchins, and Herblock. (Volume 12)
  - Clippings of news stories by Ed Harris and Others., 1956; Harris' news stories were filed from the West Coast for the St. Louis Dispatch; includes correspondence from Herblock, Leslie Caron, Malcolm Cowley, and Michigan Governor G. Mennen Williams. (Volume 13)
  - Clippings of news stories by Ed Harris and Others., 1957; Harris' news stories were filed from the West Coast for the St. Louis Dispatch; includes correspondence from St. Louis Mayor Raymond P. Tucker, Ethan A. H. Shapley, Chancellor of Washington University in St. Louis. (Volume 14)
  - Clippings entitled "A Critique of the Los Angeles Press", 1958; exhibit scrapbook for master's thesis. (Volume 15)
  - Clippings of "Adam and Eve", 1961; personal advice column, written by Adam and Eve Lowell (Mr. and Mrs. Edward A. Harris) (Volume 16)